<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference paper on Owen Dwyer</title>
    <link>https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/categories/conference-paper/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conference paper on Owen Dwyer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/categories/conference-paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning over Health Records with Vadalog: a Rule-based Approach to Patient Pathways</title>
      <link>https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/publications/2023-09-ruleml/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/publications/2023-09-ruleml/</guid>
      <description>👥 Owen P. Dwyer, Teodoro Baldazzi, Jim Davies, Emanuel Sallinger and Adriano Vlad
📕 17th International Rule Challenge @ RuleML+RR 2023
In recent years, the scale of biomedical and healthcare data has grown exponentially, leading to companies building large enterprise knowledge graphs as well as scalable and intelligent processing systems to exploit them. In this high-stakes domain, the transparency of data-driven processes is paramount to ensure high levels of trustworthiness and accountability for patient safety.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Profiling IoT-based Botnet Traffic using DNS</title>
      <link>https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/publications/2019-12-botnets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.owendwyer.co.uk/publications/2019-12-botnets/</guid>
      <description>👥 Owen P. Dwyer, Angelos K. Marnerides, Vasileios Giotsas, Troy Mursch
📕 IEEE GLOBECOM 2019
📄 Full paper
Internet-wide security and resilience have traditionally been subject to large-scale DDoS attacks initiated by various types of botnets. Since the Mirai outbreak in 2016 myriads of Mirai-alike IoT-based botnets have emerged. Such botnets rely on Mirai’s base malware code and they infiltrate vulnerable IoT devices on an Internet-wide scale such as to instrument them to perform large-scale attacks such as DDoS.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
